Dave F. Kleinschmidt

⊠ dave.f.kleinschmidt@gmail.com davekleinschmidt.com github.com/kleinschmidt

I'm a cognitive and data scientist with more than 10 years of experience creating insights from large, complex datasets using computational tools, and communicating those insights to diverse stakeholders. I have a passion for making computational tools broadly useful through open source software and straightforward and intuitive presentation of difficult computational ideas through written publications and oral presentations.

Experience

2018–present Assistant Professor of Psychology, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ.

Direct computational cognitive science lab; Supervise graduate research assistants and staff.

Design, implement (custom node.js+MongoDB backend), and analyze data (using R and Julia) from online behavioral experiments

Design and implement machine learning models of human cognition.

2013-present **Open source maintainer**, *JuliaStats organization*, Distributed/remote.

> Maintain and develop open source software for statistical modeling in Julia language. Write code and documentation, review contributions, manage releases and automated testing/CI.

> Primary developer of StatsModels.jl, used in 100+ packages to transform tabular data to numerical

2016–2018 CV Starr Postdoctoral Fellow, Princeton Neuroscience Institute, Princeton, NJ.

Implemented custom Bayesian nonparametric models of human perception and categorization. Co-designed and ran weekly open workshop on statistical methods and philosophy for PhD students and other post-docs (regression, hierarchical models, Bayesian methods)

2010–2016 PhD research, Brain and Cognitive Sciences, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY. Created novel Bayesian theory of perceptual learning for speech, implemented with MCMC sampler

in custom R code and Stan.

Developed javascript platform for web-based auditory psychophysics experiments.

Lead machine learning analysis of multimodal data from brain imaging (fMRI) experiments of human perceptual learning (with Matlab).

2009–2010 **Baggett Fellow**, *Linguistics*, *University of Maryland*, College Park, MD.

Designed and taught one-day workshop on mixed-effects models and ANOVA

Research on penalized matrix factorization (sparse coding) models of statistical learning (presented at Neurobiology of Language meeting, 2010).

Education

2010–2016 Ph.D. Brain and Cognitive Sciences, University of Rochester, Rochester, NY.

2005–2009 B.A. Mathematics, concentration Cognitive Science, Williams College, Williamstown, MA, Summa cum laude, highest honors in Cognitive Science.

Skills

Statistics Linear/logistic regression, mixed-effects Bayesian MCMC, sequential MC, nonparametrics,

models, nonparametric tests inference variational inference

Workflow Jupyter notebooks, Rmarkdown, pandoc, Machine Predictive models, classification, cluster-

> make, git, github, TravisCI, docker, AWS Learning ing, NLP

Programming Languages

Julia DataFrames.jl, GLM.jl, MixedModels.jl, R tidyverse (dplyr/purrr/tidyr), ggplot2, Plots.jl/Gadfly.jl lme4/brms, rstan

Python numpy, pandas, scikit-learn Javascript Node.js/express, frontend/JQuery

Linux bash, zsh, git, server/desktop misc. (Postre)SQL, MongoDB, Matlab, Java, Lisp, Perl, LATEX

Grants and awards

- 2017 Glushko Dissertation Prize, Cognitive Science Society.
- 2015 F31 National Research Service Award, NIH NICHD.
- 2010 National Graduate Research Fellowship, NSF.

Selected Publications

- 2020 Wu*, M.-H., **Kleinschmidt***, **D. F.**, Emberson, L., Doko, D., Edelman, S., Jacobs, R., & Raizada, R. Cortical transformation of stimulus-space in order to linearize a linearly inseparable task. *Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience, Early Access*, 1–13. https://doi.org/10.1162/jocn_a_01533
- 2019 **Kleinschmidt, D. F.** Structure in talker variability: How much is there and how much can it help? *Language, Cognition and Neuroscience*, *34*(1), 43–68. https://doi.org/10.1080/23273798. 2018.1500698
 - Kleinschmidt, D. F., & Hemmer, P. A Bayesian model of memory in a multi-context environment. In A. Goel, C. Seifert, & C. Freksa (Eds.), *Proceedings of the 41st Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society*. Cognitive Science Society. osf.io/vuksn/
- 2018 Kleinschmidt, D. F. Learning distributions as they come: Particle filter models for online distributional learning of phonetic categories. In T. T. Rogers, X. Rau, X. Zhu, & C. Kalish (Eds.), Proceedings of the 40th Annual Conference of the Cognitive Science Society (pp. 1933–1938). Cognitive Science Society. https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/dymc8
 - **Kleinschmidt, D. F.**, Weatherholtz, K., & Jaeger, T. F. Sociolinguistic perception as inference under uncertainty. *Topics in Cognitive Science*, 10(4), 818–834. https://doi.org/10.1111/tops. 12331
- 2016 **Kleinschmidt, D. F.**, & Jaeger, T. F. Re-examining selective adaptation: Fatiguing feature detectors, or distributional learning? *Psychonomic Bulletin & Review*, 23(3), 678–691. https://doi.org/10.3758/s13423-015-0943-z
 - Pajak, B., Fine, A. B., **Kleinschmidt, D. F.**, & Jaeger, T. F. Learning additional languages as hierarchical probabilistic inference: Insights from first language processing. *Language Learning*, 66(4), 900–944. https://doi.org/10.1111/lang.12168
- 2015 **Kleinschmidt, D. F.**, & Jaeger, T. F. Robust speech perception: Recognize the familiar, generalize to the similar, and adapt to the novel. *Psychological Review*, 122(2). https://doi.org/10.1037/a0038695
- 2014 Salverda, A. P., **Kleinschmidt, D. F.**, & Tanenhaus, M. K. Immediate effects of anticipatory coarticulation in spoken-word recognition. *Journal of Memory and Language*, 71(1), 145–163. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jml.2013.11.002
 - Zaki, S. R., & Kleinschmidt, D. F. Procedural memory effects in categorization: Evidence for multiple systems or task complexity? *Memory & cognition*, 42(3), 508–24. https://doi.org/10.3758/s13421-013-0375-9
- 2011 Croft, W., Bhattacharya, T., **Kleinschmidt, D. F.**, Smith, D. E., & Jaeger, T. F. Greenbergian universals, diachrony, and statistical analyses. *Linguistic Typology*, *15*(2), 433–453. https://doi.org/10.1515/LITY.2011.029

^{*} Indicates equal contributions.